foreign
[Music]
welcome back to political Misfits on
radio Sputnik where we bring you news
politics and culture without the red and
blue treatment my name is Michelle Witte
I am here with John kiriaku and we are
talking a little bit about Cuba we're
talking about Cuba uh I have to talk
about Havana syndrome and the black hole
that has been sucked into oh yeah and um
immigration and what all of these
factors have to do with the U.S
relationship with Cuba joining us for
this conversation is Arnold August he's
a journalist based in Montreal he's an
author uh he contributes to the Canada
files he contributes to press tv he's on
the uh he's a member of the black
Alliance For Peace solidarity Network
Arnold thanks for joining us
all right we'll have to pick him back up
that gives me a minute to um well you
know what John I'm gonna start with you
because so
the U.S uh Embassy in Havana has been
basically closed it hasn't been yes you
know providing visas or any Consular
Services since
2017. outrageous and that is when we all
first heard about Havana syndrome
um it is now opened it's going to start
processing immigrant visas etc etc but
even NPR when they were talking about
this this morning you could tell even
they were a little bit sheepish about
the fact that there has been no
resolution none to Havana syndrome none
one of the um NPR Talking Heads this
morning uh they didn't describe it at
all you know it's just glossed over as a
mysterious health conditions okay move
on uh one of them just said that yeah
the name sounds very mysterious yeah oh
how ridiculous yeah sounds like it's
probably maybe a like mystery novel or
something or a work of fiction anyway so
I you know I want to stop and talk a
little bit about what happened five
years ago that made us close this
Embassy and I'll freak out about magic
Russian energy weapons and pass a bill
making sure some of the already most
privileged people in our society have
access to Better Health Care and more
money right and so you know what
happened to Havana syndr you know I
guess the bad guys just stopped doing it
we're all supposed to forget I thought
it was crickets well yeah but of course
it wasn't crickets because it wasn't
Cricket you know what I mean like right
maybe it was crickets it's as plausible
more plausible than the you know
mysterious energy weapons but it's like
yeah so
if you were a Havana syndrome believer
which is a apparently uh you know
tail to toe or whatever head to toe of
the federal government yep we all
believe that some adversary has mystery
weapons that can make us terribly well
that's right or not so terribly sick
from a distance right oh well I guess
they just stopped doing it when they
when we figured it out I mean how should
people feel about this yeah about the
fact that Havana Syndrome has just been
brushed under the rug I've Got a Theory
and I really do believe in my own Theory
here I believe that there are some
people who are unusually sensitive to
the Myriad of waves that are in the air
at any given time right uh whether it's
you know radio waves or 5G or whatever
that it's not this mysterious uh
bio weapon that's been developed by the
Russians or the Chinese or the Iranians
or the Cubans or the Israelis or
whomever yeah or by arpa for that matter
I think there are some people that are
just sensitive to all the garbage that's
in the air yeah and they suffer from it
yeah you know there's a county in
Western Virginia Highland County that
um purposely doesn't have any of this
stuff that's because that's where the
military has these enormous dishes
pointed up to space to listen for you
know alien signals and life and stuff
yeah there's no cable TV there are no
cell phone towers there's nothing it's
like I and I I've been there friends of
mine have a farm there I went for the
weekend I thought I was gonna you know
commit suicide because there's no I mean
there's there's nothing you there's
nothing to do except you walk around
horribly yeah that's not all it's
cracked up to be dig a hole you know
marvel at What Lies Beneath the surface
of the soil but the Washington Post
Magazine did an article about Highland
County Virginia saying that people who
suffer from these sensitivities to radio
waves have moved to Highland County and
they're and their uh symptoms uh go away
yeah so I think that there's something
yeah I think people didn't the people
who were disputing the idea that Havana
syndrome was the result of some kind of
attack we're not disputing that people
were experiencing symptoms no there's
medical evidence that they've gotten
traumatic brain injuries
I'm not going to tell you you didn't
have a tummy ache but I am going to tell
you wasn't the result of a mystery
weapon that we have also just decided
that we're not that concerned about
anymore
um Arnold August I know we have you on
the line I want to get into Cuba
specifically but do you want to talk
about how do you think people should
feel about Havana syndrome apparently
being sort of consigned to the the
Dustbin of History
well I think uh what both of you said
are are right I mean I think the
American people may add the Canadian
people because Justin Trudeau uh
government followed the uh Trump
Administration and also imposed sort of
sanctions against their Consular
services in Nevada so I guess we could
say people in North America have to wake
up to the fact that whole thing is that
syndrome was a farce that was worked out
I don't know who but definitely in the
interest of the Trump Administration uh
who had uh promised that he will stand
up to the dictators and the in Venezuela
and Cuba and all that and not so what he
calls it Democratic party opening up to
uh to Cuba so it came the the initial
sanctions came in the very month when
Trump started his mandate back in
January 2017 I believe so like the
question is people can ask why should
Cuba who has been trying since 1959 to
have better relations good relations
with you but definitely want to like
okay listen why should the Cubans get
into a serious uh contradiction with the
United States by trying to disorient
their staff or somehow poison their
minds or not just that alone it does not
make sense Cuba never had it and it just
and did not have an interest in doing
that now uh so I think we have to say
that you know all those who've been
saying since 2017 that there was an
issue they owe it it's including the
high level so-called scientists they owe
it to the public opinion and North
America to explain well as you said what
happened you know if you're opening the
Crosshair Services now that means that
we to assume that that whole thing as
many people have correctly
said that it is made up or exaggerated
by by the United States and some
so-called uh scientific uh thing types
yeah yeah cos an explanation
all right let's talk about migration
because that's what really this is
probably all about
um this is according to reports this is
the biggest migratory flight from Cuba
in decades I am pretty sure the the
morning podcast on NPR said it's
possible up to two percent of the
Island's population has left
um a lot of Cubans are trying to come to
the United States and as I mentioned
earlier in the show Cubans are the
second largest nationality after
Mexicans attempting to cross the border
uh NPR tells us the growing migration is
due to a complex array of factors
including economic energy and political
crises and it only alludes to the U.S
relationship with Cuba as being
historically tense that's their freezing
for the entire uh seven decades yeah so
I wanted to ask you Arnold if you could
talk to us a little bit about
um you know this flight from Cuba and
some of the uh crises driving it and
whether NPR should have maybe explained
a little bit more about the U.S
relationship with Cuba in order to
explain those factors
yeah that's that's very good you know
historically they mentioned historically
been the case between Cuba and the state
in fact everyone knows in 1960 uh
Mallory or 61 Secretary of State Mallory
have said that we have to impose
sanctions against Cuba to make the
economy scream and make sure that the
people in Cuba are deprived of all basic
necessities become poor and but blame
that on the Cuban government now with
regards to how this whole thing affects
migration at this time like many people
say well the American blockade against
Cuba does not work well I'm sorry to say
but it does work to a large extent we
just look at migration of course it has
not worked by overthoring the government
we have that straight but it has worked
and contributing substantially to the
economic degradation that human people
have been going through all of these
years and part of this uh decline sharp
Decline and economic possibilities
despite the uh advances they made before
is that there are that there is an
increase in Immigration that before this
current wave and now in the last few
months even before that there was
regular immigration from Cuba to the
United States and I'm in contact you
know with my Cuban friends I've lived
there for quite some time and this
creates major frustrations a month a
very important section of the Cuban
population families many families who
have at least one person sort of exiled
in the United States and this uh it sort
of it tears away from the uh morale from
the happiness that tuba Cuban people
would normally be able to enjoy in their
society so it does eat away from the
moral fabric of the student society and
the latest I think NPR said and
correctly so this latest wave of
immigration is last month I believe was
more than a Cuba experience for decades
of the whole year previous so it's very
seriously
there's you know we talked about a
social Society one of the main features
of social Society is being happy that
you're happy in life and no one can deny
this immigration caused by the United
States takes away a certain important
portion of this happiness so it Bears
the blood it does affect the Human
Society yeah is the Cuban government uh
attempting to do anything about
migrations specifically
uh yeah well in fact there is I just
came across an article that was just
published today interesting article
which the an American specialist uh
William uh William uh Lebron he said
that there's first the Biden himself has
just uh
nominated at Christopher Dodd who has be
his special uh Emissary to Latin America
and specifically to Cuba so the
discussion behind the scenes apparently
according to this new report that just
suffered yes surface yesterday there is
some discussion behind the scenes
discussion between Cuba and the United
States that includes all major issues
including
immigration now what is interesting and
I find a bit dangerous that discussion
has even gone so far as to possibly at
cubic entertain or consider
releasing some of those people who are
arrested following the July 21st uh
Uprising or protests or whatever last
year now if Cuba is going to consider
releasing some of these people who were
tried and convicted for variety and
carrying out violent activities against
the state but you know I don't think
Cuba will do it the fact that it's being
considered in the discussion and mind
you you know I see that's being a major
mistake because if Cuba gave a best
right to try and convict people who
violated the Cuban Constitution if they
let them go or in any way reduce their
incentives substantially this would
increase the uh the the those people who
want to pursue this type of color
Revolution or resume change they do it
like well well if we could carry on the
consequences are not that bad we want go
to jail but I'm not saying that tumors
are going to do that but it's
interesting for us to take note that our
discussions going on right now and I
know Cuba is very desperate to resolve
the problem of immigrations for the
reasons I just suggested and I think
United States also wants to produce
immigration because play uh Havoc well
yeah the current administration of all
these people coming into the United
States this is something that I think is
interesting because yeah I think that um
uh you know other reports note that
migration is actually putting pressure
on the United States to open more
dialogue with Cuba uh because Joe Biden
has not found a way to reduce
immigration uh other than by falling
back on you know tactics to more
effectively expel migrants he hasn't
been able to put through any kind of
immigration reform I think you could
argue that he hasn't tried very hard and
now with Cubans being a such a
significant percentage of the number of
migrants you know it would seem like
improving relations with the island and
I mean I think it's probably too early
to hope for any kind of end to an
embargo but it does seem like yeah
immigration could actually pressure the
United States to come to the table and
talk to Cuba and make some concessions I
wanted to ask you about that
I think you're right you know this
immigration from uh Cuba immigration
from a Cuba to United States is building
up to such a proportion that before we
talked we heard about people from
Nicaragua outside of Salvador Central
America and and Haiti but now Cuba is
one of the most important sources of
illegal immigration from different parts
of Latin America for example Mexico into
Cuba and all of those illegal
small ships small vessels uh going from
Havana to Miami so this is something
that uh Biden does not want I think is
it worth it I mean by normally the
United States as you know they they like
to welcome refugees from a country such
as Cuba to maintain or their basic uh
narrative ah look communism work
communism does not work social socialism
because now we're looking at all the
people coming to this nice calculus
country in the United States to five
feet yes that is an advantage for the uh
Biden Administration as it as it has
been for all previous administrations
but the fact is I think Biden must be
away the possibility that this very
small uh portion of the Cuban population
growing the United States are going to
just you know uh go overboard to log
United States and put down the Cuban
government this really uh an important
point for Biden to the extent of
allowing more and more of these Cuban
images to come to to United States I
don't think so I mean I don't think that
the the political positive blowback for
United States of you know socialism is
failing capitalism is working I don't
think that they are really they I don't
think they think that this is going to
become the main outcome of this current
increase so rather be the main outcome
would be to destabilize part of the
United States especially in Florida and
along the border with Mexico which I
Biden does not want to do yeah yeah I
wanted to ask also what what do Cubans
need right there was a uh a terrible
disaster I mean I think the energy
crisis they're alluding to is a result
of that huge fire that there was at a uh
Refinery that some other countries sent
more help for so what what do Cubans
actually need in you know in the
immediate moment
question to be quite Frank I speak to my
you know I haven't been able to go there
lately but I speak to my children
colleagues pretty often I mean several
days a week and the main overall concern
is very clear is the price the inflation
is rapid there like okay yeah yesterday
I went to buy rice for this today it's
200 hard there is a very important
increase in price of basic Commodities
that is mainly of food and also they are
still deprived of electricity for
several hours a day seven days a week as
a result of that metances fire that you
just mentioned so you know tube is what
to be able to buy food and have
electricity as much as possible during
the daytime this is the main feature and
you know even though of course they all
blame the United States these
long-lasting blockade and creating a
situation and then you had the pandemic
the loss of massive tourist
funds coming uh as a result of a tourism
to Cuba also was lost for almost a whole
year during the pandemic so this whole
you know poisonous atmosphere of
accumulating blockade affects the
matanzas fire uh the closing down of
tourist industry for a couple of years
and all that all this is sort of
creating a situation where the economic
situation as my friend said it's antenna
it's very very bad now what can the
children do to stop this rapid rapid
installation well there's also problems
and the Cubans recognize it of
corruption yeah you have people like
professional what they call it called
Heroes professional uh people who go
into the there's long lives up for food
right yeah so there are people who go
there they take a spot there someone has
to pay them they stay in that spot they
get the food they want to buy well the
other person who back can go back to
their family and there's also and this
is recognized by yes canal in his speech
only about a week ago that there's a
major problem of people on a black bar
that buy material especially food and
then resell it at a much higher price so
they're you know I don't want to be
pessimistic but let us face the fact of
as friends of the Cuban Revolution as I
am that that there's a very serious
situation in terms of the economy in
terms of corruption and uh how they will
deal with it at this time I don't know
it is very difficult yeah yeah Arnold
August thank you so much for joining us
that was journalist and author Arnold
August do you want to tell our listeners
where they can go to find your more
recent work
yeah just put in my website it's triple
w
uh Arnold august.com simple great thank
you so much for joining us really
appreciate it